<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Zookeeper | Welcome to My Nerd World]]></title>
  <link href="http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/categories/zookeeper/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://beingasysadmin.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-07T09:21:50+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://beingasysadmin.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Deepak M Das]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Docker Cluster using Multiple Mesos Masters]]></title>
    <link href="http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2014/08/15/managing-docker-cluster-using-multiple-mesos-masters/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-15T16:44:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2014/08/15/managing-docker-cluster-using-multiple-mesos-masters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my previous <a href="http://beingasysadmin.wordpress.com/2014/06/27/managing-docker-clusters-using-mesos-and-marathon/">blog</a>, i've described how to manage Docker cluster using Mesos and Marathon. It was using a single Mesos Master. But for production, we cannot go with a single Mesos master, as it will result in a sinlge point of failure. Mesos supports Multi master via Zookeeper. So in this blog i'm going to explain how to setup a Multi Master Mesos Cluster using Zookeper for Automatic promotion of Mesos master when the current Active Mesos Master fails. This time i'm going to setup 3 Zookeeper services and 2 Mesos Master on a single Vagrant box.</p>

<h1>Setting up ZooKeeper Cluster</h1>

<p>First lets download the the latest stable Zookeeper source code.</p>

<pre><code>$ wget http://mirrors.ukfast.co.uk/sites/ftp.apache.org/zookeeper/stable/zookeeper-3.4.6.tar.gz
</code></pre>

<p>Now extract the tar file and create 3 copies of the same, say zookeeper1, zookeeper2 and zookeeper3. Also Zookeeper needs Java on the machine, so let's install java dependencies.</p>

<pre><code>$ apt-get install openjdk-7-jdk openjdk-7-jre
</code></pre>

<p>Now inside, the extracted zookeeper source folder, we need to create a config file. So in our case, inside each Zookeeper folder, we need a <code>zoo.cfg</code> file.</p>

<p>For zookeeper1 folder,</p>

<pre><code># content of zoo.cfg
tickTime=2000
dataDir=/var/lib/zookeeper1/
clientPort=2181
initLimit=5
syncLimit=2
server.1=localhost:2888:3888
server.2=localhost:2889:3889
server.3=localhost:2890:3890
</code></pre>

<p>For zookeeper2 folder,</p>

<pre><code># content of zoo.cfg
tickTime=2000
dataDir=/var/lib/zookeeper2/
clientPort=2182
initLimit=5
syncLimit=2
server.1=localhost:2888:3888
server.2=localhost:2889:3889
server.3=localhost:2890:3890
</code></pre>

<p>For zookeeper3 folder,</p>

<pre><code>    # content of zoo.cfg
tickTime=2000
dataDir=/var/lib/zookeeper3/
clientPort=2183
initLimit=5
syncLimit=2
server.1=localhost:2888:3888
server.2=localhost:2889:3889
server.3=localhost:2890:3890
</code></pre>

<p>Here, since the 3 zookeeper services are running on the same host, i've assigned separate ports. If the zookeeper are running on separate instances, then we can have the same ports for all of the zookeeper nodes. There are two port numbers. The first followers use to connect to the leader, and the second is for leader election.</p>

<p>Now we can start the Zookeeper in Foreground using the <code>./bin/zkServer.sh start-foreground</code> from each of the 3 zookeeper folders. <code>netstat -nltp | grep 288</code> will display the port of the zookeeper service which is the current master among the cluster. We can also check the connectivity using the zookeepr client binary available in the zookeeper source folder. Once zookeeper cluster is UP, we can go ahead setting up Mesos.</p>

<h1>Setting up Multiple Mesos Masters</h1>

<p>Mesossphere team has already built packages for Mesos,Marathon and Deimos. So one of my Mesos master will be from the package. But i also wanted to play with the Mesos Source, so i decided to build Mesos from the source. So my second Mesos Master will be from the scratch.</p>

<p>First Master from the Mesosphere package.</p>

<pre><code>$ apt-key adv --keyserver keyserver.ubuntu.com --recv E56151BF

$ DISTRO=$(lsb_release -is | tr '[:upper:]' '[:lower:]')

$ CODENAME=$(lsb_release -cs)

# Add the repository
$ echo "deb http://repos.mesosphere.io/${DISTRO} ${CODENAME} main" | sudo tee /etc/apt/sources.list.d/mesosphere.list

$ apt-get -y update

$ apt-get -y install mesos marathon deimos
</code></pre>

<p>Now we need to define the Zookeeper cluster details so that Mesos master and slave can connect. Edit <code>/etc/mesos/zk</code> and add <code>zk://localhost:2181,localhost:2182,localhost:2183/mesos</code>. More details about Zookeeper URL is available <a href="https://github.com/deepakmdass88/mesos-doc-test/blob/master/Using-ZooKeeper.textile">here</a>. Also More details about installing Mesos from Mesosphere's Debian package is available in their <a href="http://mesosphere.io/docs/getting-started/debian-install/">website</a>.</p>

<p>So now we have one master ready, we can start the Mesos Master, Mesos Slave and Marathon. ANd esnure that they can connect to our Zookeeper cluster properly. We can also see the connection status in the stdout of the zookeeper process as they are running in foreground.</p>

<p>Now building the second Mesos master from scratch. First let's download the Mesos Source Code.</p>

<pre><code>$ wget http://archive.apache.org/dist/mesos/0.19.0/mesos-0.19.0.tar.gz

$ tar xvzf mesos-0.19.0.tar.gz &amp;&amp; cd mesos-0.19.0

$ ./bootstrap &amp;&amp; ./configure --prefix=/usr/local/mesos

$ make &amp;&amp; make install
</code></pre>

<p>Once the Compilation is succeeded, we can start the new Mesos Master service. The default port 5050 is used by the existing master, so we need to run this new service on a different port.</p>

<pre><code>$ /usr/local/mesos/sbin/mesos-master --zk=zk://localhost:2181,localhost:2182,localhost:2183/mesos --port=5054 --quorum=1 --registry=in_memory --work_dir=/var/lib/mesos/
</code></pre>

<p>Once the new Mesos Master is up, we can create a test container via Marathon Rest API. Create a simple json file called ubuntu.json</p>

<pre><code>{
    "container": {
    "image": "docker:///libmesos/ubuntu",
    "options" : []
  },
  "id": "ubuntu",
  "instances": "1",
  "cpus": ".3",
  "mem": "200",
  "uris": [ ],
  "cmd": "while sleep 10; do date -u +%T; done"
}


$ curl -X POST -H "Content-Type: application/json" localhost:8080/v2/apps -d@ubuntu.json
</code></pre>

<p>This will launch a single container. We can check the status of the container via the Marathon UI as well as via RestAPI also. Now comes the critical part for Production, What happens when the master fails. Mesos Documentation says, if the current master fails, in a Multi master Mesos Cluster, Zookeeper will elect a new Master, in our case the second Mesos master service. And Mesos Claims that the running services will not get crashed and the status will be taken by the newly promoted master. In our case, we have a Docker container running as a long running service.</p>

<p><img src="https://beingasysadmin.files.wordpress.com/2014/06/marathon-1.png?w=6400"></p>

<p>First i'll stop one of the Mesos master service,</p>

<pre><code>$ service mesos-master stop
</code></pre>

<p>Now immidiately on the stdout of the Zookeeper, we can see the logs corresponding to the Election process. Below is the same,</p>

<pre><code>I0814 19:41:07.889044  9093 contender.cpp:243] New candidate (id='7') has entered the contest for leadership
2014-08-14 19:41:07,896:9088(0x7ff8e2ffd700):ZOO_INFO@check_events@1750: session establishment complete on server [127.0.0.1:2183], sessionId=0x347d606d0d90003, negotiated timeout=10000
I0814 19:41:07.899509  9092 group.cpp:310] Group process ((10)@10.0.2.15:5054) connected to ZooKeeper
I0814 19:41:07.900049  9092 group.cpp:784] Syncing group operations: queue size (joins, cancels, datas) = (0, 0, 0)
I0814 19:41:07.900069  9092 group.cpp:382] Trying to create path '/mesos' in ZooKeeper
I0814 19:41:07.915621  9092 detector.cpp:135] Detected a new leader: (id='6')
I0814 19:41:07.915699  9092 group.cpp:655] Trying to get '/mesos/info_0000000006' in ZooKeeper
I0814 19:41:07.920266  9094 network.hpp:423] ZooKeeper group memberships changed
I0814 19:41:07.920910  9094 group.cpp:655] Trying to get '/mesos/log_replicas/0000000003' in ZooKeeper
I0814 19:41:07.924144  9095 network.hpp:461] ZooKeeper group PIDs: { log-replica(1)@10.0.2.15:5054 }
I0814 19:41:07.926575  9092 detector.cpp:377] A new leading master (UPID=master@10.0.2.15:5054) is detected
I0814 19:41:07.926679  9092 master.cpp:957] The newly elected leader is master@10.0.2.15:5054 with id 20140814-194033-251789322-5050-8808
</code></pre>

<p>As per the above logs, the second Mesos Master running at port 5054 was promoted as New Mesos Master. This will be reflected to Marathon also. We can go to the Marthon UI and make sure that the Docker process that we have started using the old Mesos master is still running fine. We can even try making some scaling changes and can make sure that the new master can alter the process.</p>

<p>In my testing, i've tried stoping each of the service and ensured that only one Mesos master is running and also tried scaling the Apps from one Master service to make sure that the new Master was able to keep track of all these changes. The results were quite promising. Mesos + Marrthon + Docker indeed is killer combo. We can really built a cross vendor independent cluster with scaling capabilites.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
