<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: icinga | Welcome to My Nerd World]]></title>
  <link href="http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/categories/icinga/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://beingasysadmin.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-15T01:09:14+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://beingasysadmin.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Deepak M Das]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using SNMP with Icinga]]></title>
    <link href="http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2013/02/26/using-snmp-with-icinga/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-26T21:55:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2013/02/26/using-snmp-with-icinga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my previous i explained how to set up the Icinga monitoring system on Debian based machine. In this i will be explaining on how to use SNMP with icinga. Using SNMP we can get various info from a remote machine which can be used to icinga.</p>

<p>On the remote server we need to install the snmp server. In ordr to check whether the snmp is working fine, we can install the snmp client also on the same machine.</p>

<pre><code>apt-get install snmp snmp-server
</code></pre>

<p>From Debian Wheezy onwards, the <strong><em>snmp-mibs</em></strong> package has been removed from the debian repositories. But we can download the debian file from the squeeze repo. Since it has only a few depenencies and they can be installed from the debian repositories, we can manually install the mibs package. But in Ubuntu mibs package is still available in their repositories.</p>

<p>Once the package is installed we can run the <strong><em>download-mibs</em></strong> to install all the necessary mibs. Now once the snmpd package is installed, we need to comment the MIBS option in the <code>/etc/snmp/snmp.conf</code>. And define the basic settings like, location, contact etc in the <code>snmpd.conf</code> file. We can define the ip to which snmp should listen either in the snmpd.conf file or in the <code>/etc/default/snmp</code> file as an extra option. Once the settings are modified, we can start the snmpd service.</p>

<p> So now the service will listening on the port <em>631</em> on the ip which we defined, by default <strong>127.0.0.1</strong>. We can also enable authentication for snmp service, so that the snmp clients which passes the authentication will be able to get the result from the snmp service.</p>

<p>Once the snmp service has started on the remote server, we can test the snmp onnectivity from our icinga server using the nagios' <code>check_snmp plugin</code>. Once we are able to get results from the snmp service, we can deploy tese snmp services into our icinga host configurations to get the results from the remote server's using the <strong><em>check_snmp command</em></strong>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Monitoring server's using Icinga]]></title>
    <link href="http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2013/02/25/monitoring-servers-using-icinga/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-25T21:44:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2013/02/25/monitoring-servers-using-icinga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week we had severe outage in our US vps. The <em>load</em> was getting too high in the server, since it's a hosting server, and so many of our clients are hosting their DNS, website and mail server in it. So i decided to implement a monitoring system. And i decided it to extend it to all of our client server's so that we can have a fully fledged monitoring system in our company. I'm a great fan of Sensu and i play with it regularly, but this time i decided to setup <a href="http://icinga.org">Icinga</a> monitoring system, which can be used any System admin very easily. In this post i will be explaining on how to setup the <strong><em>icinga</em></strong> with it's newest web interface called icinga-web. This setup works perfectly in <em>Debian</em> based OS. In my next post, i will be explaining on how to setup <em>SNMP</em> to work with icinga.</p>

<p>By default Ubuntu and Debian repositories has icinga packages.</p>

<pre><code>$ apt-get install icinga icinga-cgi icinga-common icinga-core icinga-idoutils icinga-web icinga-web-pnp mysql-server
</code></pre>

<p>Once the installation is completed, by default icinga has already created a config file for the local host, which can be found in <code>/etc/icinga/objects/</code>. Now we can access the default icinga web interface with <code>http://yoursystemip/icinga</code>. The default user will be <strong><em>icingaadmin</em></strong> and password will be the default password which we have setup during the installation. Now we can create the config files for other hosts and we should restart the icinga service. This will add the host's to our default web interface. All the check commands are defined in the <code>/etc/nagios-plugins/config/</code> folder.</p>

<p>Now we need to set a contact so that icinga can send alerts to the specified email id. In the <code>/etc/icinga/objects/</code> there is a file called <strong><em>contacts_icinga.cfg</em></strong>, where we have to define the contact info.</p>

<pre><code>define contact{
    contact_name                    your_contact_name
    alias                           alias
    service_notification_period     24x7
    host_notification_period        24x7
    service_notification_options    w,u,c,r
    host_notification_options       d,r
    service_notification_commands   notify-service-by-email
    host_notification_commands      notify-host-by-email
    email                           your_contact_email_id
    }
</code></pre>

<p> The <strong><em>notify-service-by-email</em></strong> and <strong><em>notify-host-by-email</em></strong> commands are defined in the <code>/etc/icinga/commands.cfg</code> file. We can make changes to the format of the email alert by modifying this file. the "icinga-web" package will setup the basic config for the new icinga-web interface. Before starting the new interface we need to check a few settings for the new interface. First is the Database for the new interface. Ensure that the DB icinga-web and a user called icinga-web is created in the mysql. Now we need ensure that the database settings are correctly mentioned in the icinga-web settings. The settings are available in <code>/etc/icinga-web/conf.d/</code>. Now ensure that the database,user, and password are correctly mentioned in the <code>databases.xml</code> file. Now we need to ensure that the broker modules are enabled in the icinga.cfg file. comment out the below line in the icinga.cfg file to enable the idmod to enable the idomod broker module.</p>

<pre><code>broker_module=/usr/lib/icinga/idomod.so config_file=/etc/icinga/idomod.cfg
</code></pre>

<p>Also increase the log level to debug in both icinga as well as idomod, which helps to identify error if any. Now restart the icing and idomod services. Now go to the new interface by going to the following url, <code>http://ip/icinga-web</code>. the default user name is "root" and the passwod will be the one which we have given during installation</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
